Guide to the Alex Harris photographs and papers, 1970-2012 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Alex Harris photographs and papers 1970-2012 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Harris, Alex.
29 Linear Feet Approximately 15,400 Items
Documentary photographer, author, and faculty at the Center for Documentary Studies in Durham, North Carolina.
The Alex Harris Photographs and Papers span the years 1970 to 2012. The 549 black-and-white and color photographic prints are organized into the following series established by the photographer: Alaska; American South; Cuba Auto/Landscapes; Game Boy; May Day: Yale on Strike (which includes images of radical activist Bobby Seale); New Mexico/Arizona; Philadelphia Experience Corps; Portraits of Aging; and Mobile, Alabama. Harris's professional papers are housed in four additional series: Publicity and Audiovisual Materials; Correspondence; DoubleTake Files; Project Files; and Teaching Materials. The papers reflect Harris's collaborations with other photographers and writers on books and exhibitions, including anthropologist Gertrude Duby Blom, and document his career at Duke University, both as a teacher and as co-founder of the Center for Documentary Studies and its magazine, DoubleTake. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Materials are for educational use only; commercial reproduction is prohibited.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Use copies are available as surrogates for the very large prints in the Cuba Auto/Landscapes and Game Boy series, and should be used whenever possible. Please consult with a reference archivist for access to the original prints.
Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact a reference archivist before coming to use this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Alex Harris Photographs and Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift from 1992-2012.
Biographical Note
Alex Harris was born in 1949 and grew up in Atlanta, Georgia. He is married to Margaret Sartor, also a documentary photographer and educator. Harris has spent the majority of his adult life in North Carolina. His photography deals with a wide range of subject matter, documenting in particular aspects of the American South, New Mexico, Arizona, and Alaska, as well as the people and regions of Cuba. Many of his works are part of major collections, including those of The San Francisco Museum of Modern Art, The J. Paul Getty Museum in Los Angeles, The Museum of Modern Art in New York, The High Museum of Art in Atlanta, The North Carolina Museum of Art, and the Metropolitan Museum of Art. Harris has also received a variety of awards for his photography, including a Guggenheim Fellowship in Photography, a Rockefeller Foundation Humanities Fellowship, and a Lyndhurst Prize. He is a co-founder of the Center for Documentary Studies at Duke University, where he has taught documentary photography and writing since 1975. He has also published many books on documentary photography, many of which feature his own work.
Collection Overview
The Alex Harris Photographs and Papers span the years 1970-2012, from the time Harris was producing his earliest photographic work as a graduate student at Yale University, to his more recent work documenting the American South. The 413 black and white and color photographic prints in the collection are organized into the following series established by the photographer, and are described more fully in the collection guide: Alaska; American South; Cuba Auto/Landscapes; Game Boy; May Day: Yale on Strike; New Mexico/Arizona; Philadelphia Experience Corps; Portraits of Aging; and Mobile, Alabama. The images depict landscapes across the United States, the culture and society of Cuba and U.S. cities, and portraits and other shots of individuals spanning all ages, races, and origins. Among the images of Yale students on strike, there are photos of the radical activist Bobby Seale. The prints range from black-and-white gelatin silver to color archival pigmented prints printed on laser or inkjet printers; sizes range from 8x10 inch reference prints to very large 24x30 inch exhibit prints, for which smaller surrogates exist; some prints are matted.
Four other series composed mainly of non-photographic materials document other aspects of Harris's career, especially his collaborations with other photographers and writers, and his career at Duke University, both as a teacher and as co-founder of the Center for Documentary Studies (CDS) and its magazine, DoubleTake. The Publicity and Audiovisual Materials Series contains recordings of lectures as well as publicity for exhibits and publications. The extensive Correspondence Series includes not only Harris's letters but also grant applications, research notes, drafts and proofs, printed materials, and photographs. The DoubleTake Files consist mainly of materials generated during the planning stages and early years of the magazine's existence; while materials on Harris's extensive collaborations on other publications, documentary projects, and related exhibitions make up the large Project Files Series, which also includes many oral histories and interviews related to his projects. The last group in the collection, the Teaching Materials Series, comprises syllabi, student writings, and other materials from classes taught by Harris mainly through the CDS at Duke University.
Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Use copies are available as surrogates for the very large prints in the Cuba Auto/Landscapes, Game Boy, and Mobile series, and should be used whenever possible. Please consult with a reference archivist for access to the original prints.
Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Some listening copies are available and are noted in this guide. Use of other materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact a reference archivist before coming to use this material.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
Black Panther Party -- Pictorial works
Blom, Gertrude Duby -- Interviews
DoubleTake
Duke University. Center for Documentary Studies
Harris, Alex, 1949-
Seale, Bobby, 1936-
Alaska Natives -- Pictorial works
City and town life -- Alabama
City and town life -- Cuba
Computer games -- Social aspects
Documentary photography -- United States
Documentary photography -- Southern states
Duke University -- Faculty
Indigenous peoples -- Alaska -- Pictorial works
Older people -- North Carolina -- Pictorial works
Photographers -- United States -- Correspondence
Photography -- Study and teaching
Southern states -- Pictorial works
Student protesters -- Pictorial works
Student strikes -- Pictorial works
Technology and children
Yale University -- Student life
Mobile (Ala.)--Pictorial works
Alaska -- Pictorial works
Arizona -- Pictorial works
Cuba -- Pictorial works
Havana (Cuba)--Pictorial works
New Mexico -- Pictorial works
Audiocassettes
Color photographs
Digital prints
DVDs
Gelatin silver prints
Inkjet prints
Laser prints
Videocassettes
Related Material
Alex Harris's work in South Africa with fellow documentarians Bruce Payne, Paul Weinberg, Margaret Sartor, and Omar Badsha, and his work with Gertrude Duby Blom in Central America, is reflected in the following collections also held in the Rubenstein Library:
South Africa Documentary Photographs Collection, 1940s-2007 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Gertrude Duby Blom Photographs, 1950s-1980s
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Description of Collection
- Alaska Series, 1973-1978, (3 boxes)
  Contains six 16x20 inch (box 3) and 50 11x14 inch black-and-white prints (boxes 1-2). The images were made over the course of multiple trips over a five-year period to villages along the Kobuk River, located above the Arctic Circle, and fishing villages along the southern coast of the Bering Sea in Alaska. The images depict the day-to-day lives of indigenous peoples in various small Alaskan communities.
  - Alaska prints (Box 1-3)
- American South Series, 1971-1972, 1984-1985, (3 boxes)
  Fifty-six black-and-white 17x22 inch digital prints (boxes 6-7) of people and places throughout North Carolina, photographed from 1971-1972. The project was an initiative of the Institute of Policy Sciences and Public Affairs at Duke University and started as a photographic study of substandard housing and living conditions in the state. The images feature scenes and portraits of North Carolinians from counties in the eastern, central and western regions. These photographs are from very early in Harris's professional career. Additionally, the series contains 38 24x30 inch color prints (boxes 4-5) of the American South, photographed from 1984-1985. This project was funded by an award from the Lyndhurst Foundation; the images feature scenes from a variety of Southern towns.
  - American South prints (Box 4-7)
- Cuba Auto/Landscapes Series, 1998, (3 boxes)
  Contains 21 24x30 inch pigmented inkjet color prints of Cuban landscapes and city scenes taken from within the interiors of classic American cars dating from 1948-1958. Also includes one 24x30 type C lambda digital laser print on Fuji Crystal Archive Paper. Use copies for these large prints are available in Box 10. There is also a single 24x30 color print, in a 30x40 mat. No use copy is available for this print.
  - Cuba, original prints (Box 8-9)
  - Cuba, 8x10 use copies (Box 10)
  - Cuba auto, 24x30 matted print (Oimagefolder 1)
- Game Boy Series, 1997-1999, (2 boxes, 1 folder)
  Consists of 21 20x24 inch color prints, featuring the artist's son, Will, and deals with the subject of children and technology. Smaller use copies for these large prints are available in box 13. The project was provoked by the artist's observation that children, including his own, were becoming increasingly attached to hand held, portable electronic gaming devices. The series captures the artist's son in a variety of settings, both public and private, playing his Game Boy and means to explore the implications of how pre-adolescent interaction with electronics might bear out on post-adolescent human interaction and relationships. Use copies for these large prints are available in Box 10.
  - Game Boy, original prints, 1997-1999, printed 1999 (Box 11-12)
  - Game Boy, 8x10 use copies (Box 10)
- May Day: Yale on Strike Series, May, 1970, (1 box)
  Alex Harris's earliest work in the collection consists of 12 black-and-white 16x20 inch digital prints of student demonstrations at Yale University. The demonstrations came in response to the arrest of Black Panther Party leader, Bobby Seale, who was accused of ordering the murder of a supposed police informant in New Haven, CT. The series documents the demonstrations from a variety of angles and includes images of National Guard soldiers, students and university officials. These images remained unprinted for almost thirty-seven years until they were edited and printed as part of an exhibition of Alex Harris's early work at Duke University.
  - Yale student protest prints, (12 prints) (Box 13)
- New Mexico and Arizona Series, 1972-1987, 1999, 2000, (5 boxes)
  black-and-white digital prints and color prints taken by Harris in New Mexico and Arizona, printed in 1999 and 2000. There are also some images shot in Arizona at a Rainbow Gathering, a counter-culture festival (1979, printed in 1999).
  - 11x14 New Mexico and Arizona color prints, (49 prints) (Box 14-15)
  - 11x14 black-and-white digital New Mexico prints, (28 prints) (Box 16)
  - 7 11x14 Arizona Rainbow Gathering black-and-white digital prints, and 21 11x14 New Mexico black-and-white digital prints, (28 prints) (Box 17)
  - 16x20 black-and-white digital New Mexico prints, (25 prints) (Box 18)
- Philadelphia Experience Corps Series, 1999, (4 boxes)
  Contains 11x14 black-and-white prints shot by Harris on assignment to document the Experience Corps, a United States civic engagement program akin to the Peace Corps. Images feature school children and tutors interacting in various school settings in six Philadelphia city schools.
  - Philadelphia prints, (56 prints) (Box 19-22)
- Portraits of Aging Series, 1990-1992, (3 boxes)
  Contains black-and-white matted portraits of older individuals from Durham, North Carolina in their seventies, eighties and nineties. The images include biographical information and the place each portrait was taken. Also includes publicity poster for exhibit.
  - Portraits of Aging prints, (21 prints) (Box 23-25)
- Mobile, Alabama Series, 2009-2011, (1 box)
  Contains 68 archival pigmented color photographs taken by Alex Harris in Mobile, Alabama for a documentary book project co-authored with naturalist Edward O. Wilson, entitled Why We Are Here: Mobile and the Spirit of a Southern City (2012). The prints were part of an exhibit in the Mobile Museum of Art from October-January 2013.
  Images include portraits of Mobile citizens from various backgrounds; a football team's activities; Civil War re-enactors; street scenes; Mardi Gras events; and landscapes, including images of the Gulf of Mexico.
  The prints were made on an Epson 7900 stylus pro, using Epson ultrachrome hdr inks. The paper is Innova Fibraprint ultrasmooth gloss, an acid-free and lignin-free paper on a fiber base.
  [Original 2x3 foot color prints are closed to research use; 11x17 viewing prints are available in the repository.]
  - Mobile, Alabama color prints, (68 2x3' original prints) (Box 62-63)
    [Closed to research use. Viewing copies are available.]
  - Mobile, Alabama prints, (68 11x17" viewing prints) (Box 64)
- Publicity and Audiovisual Materials Series, 1971-2003, (3 boxes)
  Contains paper and a/v materials related to exhibits and publications featuring Harris's work in documentary photography. This series also includes several audio recordings of presentations by Harris. Recordings related to specific documentary projects are described with their related materials in the Project Files Series.
  [Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact a reference archivist before coming to use this collection.]
  - Printed materials, 1971-2003 (Box 26)
    Contains copies of publications which feature Harris's photography; one contains an essay on his work. Additionally, includes one folder of thumbnails and captions of particular photographic documentary projects, 1998-2001.
    - Aperture, 1978 and 1989, (2 issues) (Box 26)
    - Innovations, 2001-2002, (4 issues) (Box 26)
    - El Contemporani, 2001 (essay on Harris) (Box 26)
    - Yale Alumni Magazine, 1971 (Box 26)
    - Brochures, Cordoned Heart and Gertrude Blom, 1984 and undated (Box 26)
    - Other brochures, 1993-2000 and undated (Box 26)
    - Printed pages of thumbnail images and captions from Harris's photographic collection at Duke, 1998-2001 (Box 26)
    - Exhibition catalog, Les Suds profonds de l'Ámerique--Alex Harris, Clarence John Laughlin, Ralph Eugene Meatyard: collection le Pavillon des Images, 2010 (Box 60)
      Produced by Gilles Mora, Paris, Democratic Books. Also includes leaflet from exhibition and undated [2010] gift note from Alex Harris. Exhibition date: 2010 Oct. 21-2011 Jan. 30.
  - Audiocassette Recordings, 1982-2003 (Box 27)
    Recordings of Harris from a 1993 presentation given at the National Humanities Center, and an exhibit reception at Duke University in 2003. Titles taken from original cassette labels, with some information supplied by the archivist. Arranged chronologically.
    Lectures and speaking engagements related to Harris's photographic projects and publications, including A World Unsuspected: Portraits of Southern Childhood; A New Life: Stories and Photographs from the Suburban South; and South Africa: The Cordoned Heart project, are found in their respective subseries in the Project Files Series.
    [Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Some use copies are available and are noted. Otherwise, access to materials requires production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact a reference archivist before coming to use this collection.]
    - National Humanities Center (NHC) lecture: The Art of Documentary Photography, #247, circa 1993 (Box 27, Audiocassette RL_10060_C_012)
    - NHC lecture: Culture in Focus, #653, circa 1993, (2 copies) (Box 27, Audiocassette RL_10060_C_013)
      [Listening copy available in Box 28.]
    - Harris's presentation at the opening reception of his exhibit, Alex Harris Photographs, 1998-2000, Images From the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, September 24, 2003 (Audiocassette RL_10060_C_018)
  - Video Recordings, 1996 and 2007
    One VHS video cassette and one DVD documenting class activities and a lecture.
    [Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use copies are available. Please contact a reference archivist before coming to use this collection.]
    - "AGO AME made by the students of CA 180S, Duke University, Fall 1996, Film and Video Program and Dept. of Cultural Anthropology," VHS video cassette, 1996 (Box 62)
    - "The Idea of Cuba--Alex Harris Lecture," Nasher Museum, DVD, 2007 Nov. 16 (Box 62)
  - Use Copies of Audiocassettes and Videocassettes
    - Use copies of interviews with Gertrude Duby Blom; one use copy of NHC lecture "Culture in Focus" by Harris. (Box 28)
    - Use copies of "AGO AME" video and "The Idea of Cuba" lecture by Harris (Box 62)
- Correspondence Series, 1972-1992 and undated, (16 boxes)
  Correspondence, drafts, grant applications, research notes, photographs, printed materials, proofs, publicity, and other materials produced during Harris's work on a variety of books, conferences, exhibitions, and academic activities from the mid-1970s through the early 1990s. Some projects are covered in considerable depth, including the following: early history of the Duke University Center for Documentary Studies; Wendy Ewald and the project that eventually became the Literacy Through Photography Program; photographer Paul Kwilecki's first book, Understandings; Harris's work with Robert Coles and Helen Levitt on her In the Street: Chalk Drawings and Messages New York City, 1938-1948; and various projects involving South African photographers (see scope notes for specific boxes). Other books and exhibitions represented in this series include: I Shall Save One Land Unvisited: Eleven Southern Photographers (1978); The Last and First Eskimos (1982); The Old Ones of New Mexico (various editions); Red White Blue and God Bless You: a Portrait of Northern New Mexico (1992); and River of Traps: a Village Life (1990). Arranged alphabetically by correspondent or topic.
  - Abram-Bios, 1973-1992 and undated, (36 folders) (Box 29)
  - Black photography-CDS, 1980-1991 and undated, (30 folders) (Box 30)
  - CDS Board-Coffey, 1979-1991, (20 folders) (Box 31)
  - Coles-Dietz, 1972-1992 and undated, (28 folders) (Box 32)
    Materials include correspondence and publicity for The Cordoned Heart exhibition.
  - Doc book-Ewald, 1976-1991 and undated, (25 folders) (Box 33)
  - Ewald-Gallery 10, 1980-1992 and undated, (22 folders) (Box 34)
    Materials include seventy-five of Harris's 35mm slides and related negatives of John Hope Franklin, 1990 June-July.
  - General correspondence-ICP (International Center of Photography), 1976-1991 and undated, (38 folders) (Box 35)
  - ICP-Ledochowski, 1978-1990 and undated, (21 folders) (Box 36)
    Materials include manuscripts and correspondence with photographer Paul Kwilecki on his first book, Understandings. See also related materials filed under the book's title. Some items removed to Oversize Materials.
  - Leger-Lyndhurst, 1980-1990 and undated, (20 folders) (Box 37)
  - Lynnemeir-Mora, 1979-1992 and undated, (34 folders) (Box 38)
    One folder, A.J. Meek, removed for preservation.
  - Morgan-Resume, 1977-1992 and undated, (43 folders) (Box 39)
  - Rhodenbaugh-Smith, 1981-1992 and undated, (32 folders) (Box 40)
  - Smithsonian-South Africa, Cordoned Heart, 1981-1991 and undated, (13 folders) (Box 41)
    Materials include: correspondence with Omar Badsha and other photographers; publicity and photographic materials for various South Africa projects such as Beyond the Barricades, The Cordoned Heart and The Transported of Kwandebele For the last title, see also materials filed under David Goldblatt.
  - South Africa, Friends of Photography-Trachtenberg, 1981-1991 and undated, (21 folders) (Box 42)
    Materials include; correspondence and publicity materials for the South Africa Documentary Photography Fellowship Program; transcripts of interviews with South African documentary photographers and with South African journalist Allister Sparks.
  - Trask-Young, 1975-1990 and undated, (36 folders) (Box 43)
  - Photographs, various projects, 1972-1991 and undated, (5 folders) (Box 44)
    8x10" format prints and negatives removed from correspondence folders for flat storage. Includes work on projects with Gertrude Blom, Robert Coles, the photographs of Aden Field, and publicity photographs for The Cordoned Heart.
- DoubleTake Records Series, 1991-1998 and undated, (6 boxes)
  Files consist chiefly of correspondence with several hundred authors, photographers, and staff members during the first few years of publication of the magazine DoubleTake. Recordings derive from organizational meetings and various talks by DoubleTake founders such as Robert Coles.
  - DoubleTake files, 1986-1993 and undated
    Related materials may be found in the DoubleTake Records, 1908-1999 (bulk 1993-1999), also held in the Rubenstein Library. Materials about the magazine's founding can be found under files titled Editorial Prospectus; Whitney Ellsworth (a publishing consultant); Publication--Early Correspondence; and Quail Roost conference, and in other folders. See also the recordings in this series. Arranged alphabetically by name or topic.
    - Ackerman-Crosland, (80 folders) (Box 45)
    - Cummings-Exploris, (36 folders) (Box 46)
    - Farmer-Kellam, (65 folders) (Box 47)
    - Keohane-Mickiewicz, (57 folders) (Box 48)
    - Microscopic-Quail Roost, (44 folders) (Box 49)
    - Race-Zagajewski, (94 folders) (Box 50)
  - DoubleTake recordings, 1986-1993 and undated
    A group of eight recordings, six of which document meetings and retreats conducted in the early 1990s to discuss creation of the magazine eventually known as DoubleTake. Two microcassettes from 1986 feature Robert Coles discussing the Center for Documentary Studies. No transcripts have been discovered, but material on the early history of the magazine is present in this collection. Several tapes may derive from the same meeting at Quail Roost Retreat in 1993, although with slight variations in labeling and dating. Tapes are arranged chronologically. "MC" denotes microcassettes, "C," audiocassettes.